<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Verticals-rsses on Kevin Webber</title>
    <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Verticals-rsses on Kevin Webber</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>E-commerce</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/ecommerce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/ecommerce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What if you&amp;rsquo;re an online retailer that requires 99.9999% uptime while handling millions of page views per minute? Off-the-shelf solutions will only help you get you started, but won&amp;rsquo;t help you deal with spikes of traffic and the other realities of doing business online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concepts of Reactive Application Development and Design (RADD) have proven themselves to drive incredible business value in e-commerce. Learn how to apply these concepts to your unique business needs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finance</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/finance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Financial services is a varied industry with many diverse needs. Balancing the availability and consistency of systems is crucial, all while maintaining an inviting and predictable user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can help you leverage best-in-breed technologies in the field of stream processing, big data, and reactive programming, while also preparing your leadership for the future by advising on emerging technology topics such as blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Technology</title>
      <link>http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rocketpages.github.io/verticals/technology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Implementing effective streaming platforms is critical for technology organizations from FinTech to systems-level platform companies. Processing streams is only part of the picture; handling cascading failures, data center outages, and the other realities of modern operational environments are the tough parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have real world systems-level implementation experience on the most demanding of technology platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>